Whereas break ends a loop, the Continue
keyword skips an iteration of a loop.
Using our coins example from the previous topic
as a starting point, in the file 224-continue,
we see the same lines of code as we did in the
break topic except that, on line 6, the continue
keyword has replaced the break keyword. The goal
for this output is to show the print statement on
line 3 for all the coins in line 1, except that if
the coin is platinum, we see the print statement
on line 5 instead. With four coins, we want
four print statements. The code sort of works,
which is a widespread occurrence the first
time one runs a code block. We got the special
message for the platinum coin and the gold coin
prints, but so does the standard statement for
the platinum coin, which we do not want. Let’s
take this opportunity to run through a bit of
code analysis and troubleshooting. The first
statement in the for loop, line 2, loops through
each coin within these coins. The first statement
inside the for loop, line 3, prints the next coin
in the loop. This means that if the loop sees a
platinum coin, it prints that statement. Then,
the if statement on line 4 is evaluated. Are you
seeing the change we should make? The if block of
code should run before the print statement on line
3. In making the move, the continue portion of the
code can run if the unique platinum statement
prints. I will move the print statement on line
3 down to line 7, ensuring the indentation stays
the same. Then, I will rerun the code, and now the
code does what we need it to do, which is print
the list of coins unless the coin is platinum,
in which case, the print statement on line 5
prints and, because of the continue keyword,
the print statement on line 7 does not print. When
analyzing code, if the logic seems close to what
it needs to be but seems out of order, check to
see if your code needs rearranging. Sometimes,
moving lines of code solves a problem, which
is a big timesaver compared to rewriting code.